\documentclass[11pt, a4paper]{article}
\usepackage[utf8]{inputenc}
\usepackage[T1]{fontenc}
\usepackage{amsmath, amssymb, amsfonts, amsthm}
\usepackage{graphicx}
\usepackage{booktabs}
\usepackage{tikz}
\usetikzlibrary{shapes, arrows, positioning, fit, calc, backgrounds}
\usepackage{algorithm}
\usepackage{algorithmic}
\usepackage{hyperref}
\usepackage{geometry}
\usepackage{caption}
\usepackage{subcaption}
\usepackage{url}

\geometry{margin=1in}

\newtheorem{theorem}{Theorem}
\newtheorem{lemma}{Lemma}
\newtheorem{corollary}{Corollary}
\newtheorem{proposition}{Proposition}
\newtheorem{definition}{Definition}
\newtheorem{example}{Example}
\newtheorem{remark}{Remark}

\newcommand{\R}{\mathbb{R}}
\newcommand{\N}{\mathbb{N}}
\newcommand{\Z}{\mathbb{Z}}
\newcommand{\E}{\mathbb{E}}
\newcommand{\Var}{\mathrm{Var}}

\title{S-AI: A Multi-Agent Spatial Intelligence Framework for Hydrodynamic Flood Simulation via LLM-Orchestrated MCP Architecture}

\author{Author 1\thanks{Corresponding author. E-mail: author1@institution.edu},
Author 2, Author 3 \\
Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University Name, Country}

\date{\today}

\begin{document}

\maketitle

\begin{abstract}
Flood disasters represent one of the most consequential threats to human life and infrastructure in the 21st century, with economic losses exceeding \$80 billion annually worldwide. Traditional hydrodynamic modeling approaches, while mathematically rigorous, present prohibitive barriers to adoption due to their steep computational requirements, complex parameter calibration procedures, and limited accessibility to domain experts. This paper introduces S-AI (Spatial-AI), a production-grade multi-agent spatial intelligence platform that fundamentally transforms flood modeling paradigms through Large Language Model (LLM)-orchestrated automation. Our architecture leverages the Model Context Protocol (MCP) to integrate 42+ specialized tools across 8 microservices, enabling natural language intent parsing via GLM-5.1 that automatically orchestrates complex hydrodynamic workflows. The system implements a LISFLOOD-FP-style 2D diffusion wave model on high-resolution Digital Elevation Models (0.5m DEM, 3GB GeoTIFF, 22063$\times$36308 pixels), coupled with real-time 3D geospatial visualization using custom GLSL water shaders. Our methodology employs Delaunay triangulation for terrain mesh generation (5969 triangles from 3000 vertices), Manning's equation for flux computation with CFL stability constraints, and Chicago storm pattern temporal distributions for rainfall forcing. Experimental evaluation in Diebu County, Gansu Province (elevation range 790--1796m, EPSG:4544) demonstrates frame-by-frame inundation dynamics with temporal fidelity sufficient for emergency response planning. Comparative analysis against traditional modeling frameworks reveals an order-of-magnitude reduction in expert intervention requirements while maintaining computational accuracy. The S-AI platform represents a paradigm shift toward democratized spatial intelligence, making advanced hydrodynamic modeling accessible through conversational interfaces without sacrificing mathematical rigor or numerical stability.

\textbf{Keywords:} Multi-agent systems, hydrodynamic modeling, LLM orchestration, Model Context Protocol, flood simulation, spatial intelligence, 3D geospatial visualization.
\end{abstract}

\section{Introduction}

\subsection{Motivation: The Urgent Challenge of Flood Disasters}

Flood disasters constitute a critical global challenge, affecting approximately 2.3 billion people and causing economic losses exceeding \$800 billion between 2000 and 2020. The increasing frequency and severity of extreme precipitation events, driven by climate change, exacerbate this vulnerability. Traditional flood risk management relies heavily on hydrodynamic simulation models that solve the shallow water equations to predict inundation extent, depth, and velocity. These models are indispensable for engineering design, emergency response planning, and infrastructure resilience assessment.

However, the operational deployment of hydrodynamic models faces substantial impediments. First, the mathematical formulation of the shallow water equations requires expertise in computational fluid dynamics and numerical methods. Second, the parameter calibration process involves iterative tuning of Manning's roughness coefficients, infiltration parameters, and boundary conditions鈥攁 task that demands domain knowledge and extensive validation against historical events. Third, the computational burden associated with high-resolution simulations, particularly for 2D models over urban or complex terrain, often necessitates High Performance Computing (HPC) resources that are inaccessible to many municipalities and developing regions. Fourth, the visualization and interpretation of simulation outputs typically require specialized GIS software, creating additional barriers to stakeholder engagement.

These constraints result in a fundamental paradox: flood disasters are universally pressing, yet the most effective tools for predicting and mitigating them remain concentrated in the hands of a small community of specialists. This accessibility gap undermines flood resilience initiatives, particularly in resource-constrained regions where the need is most acute.

\subsection{Limitations of Traditional Modeling Workflows}

Contemporary hydrodynamic modeling workflows, exemplified by frameworks such as LISFLOOD-FP, TELEMAC, HEC-RAS 2D, and SWMM, follow a sequential paradigm that inherently impedes rapid iteration and scenario exploration. The typical workflow encompasses six discrete stages: data acquisition and preprocessing, mesh generation, parameter specification, model execution, post-processing, and visualization. Each stage requires specialized software tools and technical expertise, creating multiple potential failure points where novice users may abandon the process.

A critical limitation emerges from the tight coupling between stages. Modification of any upstream parameter, such as adjusting the Manning roughness coefficient or introducing alternative rainfall forcing, necessitates re-execution of all subsequent stages. This serial architecture significantly inflates the time required for sensitivity analysis, uncertainty quantification, and scenario exploration. For emergency managers operating under time constraints during flood events, this delay renders conventional models practically unusable for real-time decision support.

Furthermore, traditional frameworks exhibit limited flexibility in accommodating non-traditional data sources and analytical methods. The integration of real-time sensor networks, social media intelligence, or machine learning predictions typically requires custom implementation efforts that fall outside the scope of standard software packages. This rigidity constrains the evolution of flood modeling toward data-driven and predictive paradigms.

\subsection{The Promise of Large Language Models for Spatial Intelligence}

The recent emergence of Large Language Models (LLMs), particularly frontier models such as GPT-4, Claude, and GLM-5.1, presents an unprecedented opportunity to transform technical workflows through natural language interaction. LLMs demonstrate remarkable capabilities in code generation, task decomposition, tool selection, and procedural reasoning鈥攃apabilities that align precisely with the requirements of hydrodynamic modeling.

The Model Context Protocol (MCP) establishes a standardized framework for LLM-tool integration, enabling dynamic discovery and invocation of computational resources based on semantic intent parsing. This architecture allows users to express modeling objectives in natural language, such as "simulate a 50-year return period flood over Diebu County using a Chicago storm pattern," and receive automated orchestration of the requisite data processing, parameter specification, and simulation execution.

However, existing LLM-based systems primarily target general-purpose tasks such as web browsing, document retrieval, or code assistance. The application of LLM orchestration to spatial intelligence and hydrodynamic modeling remains largely unexplored. This gap stems from the technical complexity of spatial data structures, the stringent numerical stability requirements of hydrodynamic solvers, and the need for geospatial visualization capabilities that exceed typical LLM output modalities.

\subsection{Contributions}

This paper presents S-AI (Spatial-AI), a comprehensive multi-agent spatial intelligence platform that addresses the aforementioned limitations through LLM-orchestrated automation. Our primary contributions are as follows:

\begin{enumerate}
    \item \textbf{Architectural Innovation}: We propose and implement an MCP-native microservice architecture comprising 8 specialized servers and 42+ tools that collectively support the full hydrodynamic modeling pipeline from natural language intent to 3D visualization. This architecture enables dynamic tool discovery and orchestration through LLM-driven capability matching, eliminating the need for manual workflow specification.

    \item \textbf{Hydrodynamic Implementation}: We present a complete implementation of a 2D diffusion wave model based on the shallow water equations, integrated within an LLM-accessible framework. Our implementation includes explicit mathematical formulations for Manning's flux computation, CFL stability constraints, and Chicago storm pattern temporal distributions, ensuring numerical rigor while maintaining accessibility through natural language interfaces.

    \item \textbf{3D Geospatial Visualization}: We introduce a real-time 3D visualization system based on Three.js with custom GLSL water shaders that render hydrodynamic simulation results with physically plausible visual effects including Fresnel reflection, specular highlights, depth-gradient coloring, wave animation, and foam generation. The system supports frame-by-frame timeline playback of inundation dynamics, enabling intuitive interpretation of temporal evolution.

    \item \textbf{Empirical Validation}: We demonstrate the platform through a comprehensive case study in Diebu County, Gansu Province, using a 0.5m resolution Digital Elevation Model (3GB GeoTIFF, 22063$\times$36308 pixels) over an elevation range of 790--1796m (EPSG:4544). We characterize TIN mesh generation quality (3000 vertices, 5969 triangles), validate nodata handling strategies, and present frame-by-frame inundation results that establish computational feasibility for real-world applications.

    \item \textbf{Open Framework}: We release the complete S-AI platform as an open-source framework, enabling reproducibility, community extension, and adaptation to diverse hydrological contexts. The modular design allows seamless integration of additional tools, models, and visualization capabilities through the standardized MCP interface.
\end{enumerate}

\subsection{Paper Organization}

The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 reviews related work in hydrodynamic modeling, LLM-based multi-agent systems, and spatial intelligence. Section 3 presents the S-AI system architecture, detailing the MCP-native microservice design, LLM-driven intent routing, and data flow orchestration. Section 4 describes the hydrodynamic methodology, including mathematical formulations of the shallow water equations, Manning's flux computation, CFL stability conditions, and rainfall forcing strategies. Section 5 presents the 3D geospatial visualization system, including terrain rendering, water shader implementation, and timeline interaction mechanisms. Section 6 reports experimental results from the Diebu County case study, including mesh quality metrics, simulation parameters, and inundation dynamics. Section 7 discusses limitations, scalability considerations, and comparison with traditional workflows. Section 8 concludes the paper and outlines directions for future research.

\section{Related Work}

\subsection{2D Hydrodynamic Modeling Frameworks}

Two-dimensional hydrodynamic models solve the shallow water equations to predict flood propagation across terrain. LISFLOOD-FP, developed by researchers at the University of Bristol, employs a simplified inertial formulation that accelerates computation by neglecting convective acceleration terms while retaining the essential physics of flood wave propagation. The model uses a finite volume discretization with cell-edge flux computation based on Manning's equation, making it amenable to high-resolution applications on irregular topography. Recent extensions incorporate sub-grid representation of buildings and hydraulic structures, enabling urban flood modeling with computational efficiency.

TELEMAC, developed by the Laboratoire National d'Hydraulique et Environnement (LNHE) in France, implements a finite element solution of the full shallow water equations with advanced turbulence closure models and advection-dispersion capabilities. The system supports mesh refinement strategies that concentrate resolution in areas of interest, such as river channels and urban infrastructure, while maintaining coarser resolution in less critical regions. TELEMAC's coupling with sediment transport modules enables morphodynamic simulations of long-term channel evolution.

HEC-RAS 2D, developed by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers' Hydrologic Engineering Center, provides an integrated interface for 1D channel and 2D overland flow modeling. The solver employs an implicit finite difference scheme with adaptive time stepping to ensure stability across a wide range of flow conditions. HEC-RAS includes extensive libraries of hydraulic structures, including bridges, culverts, and gates, making it particularly suitable for infrastructure-impacted flood scenarios.

SWMM (Storm Water Management Model), developed by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, focuses on urban drainage systems through a coupled 1D channel pipe network and 2D overland flow representation. The model incorporates detailed infiltration algorithms (Green-Ampt, Horton, SCS Curve Number), allowing representation of spatially varying soil properties and land cover. Recent SWMM 5.2 releases include dynamic routing capabilities that improve representation of backwater effects and surcharging conditions.

These frameworks represent the state-of-the-art in hydrodynamic modeling but share common limitations: steep learning curves, complex GUI-based interfaces that obscure underlying workflows, limited automation capabilities, and poor integration with emerging data sources. Furthermore, none incorporate natural language interfaces or LLM-driven orchestration, maintaining the technical barriers to widespread adoption.

\subsection{LLM-Based Multi-Agent Systems}

The paradigm of LLM-based multi-agent systems has emerged as a powerful approach for complex task decomposition and execution. AutoGen, developed by Microsoft Research, introduces a framework where multiple LLM-based agents engage in structured dialogue to solve problems, with specialized agents assuming distinct roles such as user proxy, assistant, critic, and executor. The system demonstrates remarkable capabilities in code generation, mathematical reasoning, and software development through agent collaboration.

CrewAI, an open-source framework, provides a production-ready architecture for building LLM-driven agent teams with explicit role definitions, goal-oriented task allocation, and tool integration capabilities. The framework supports hierarchical agent organizations where managers coordinate worker agents, enabling scalable decomposition of complex workflows. CrewAI's design emphasizes robust error handling and memory management, critical for long-running multi-stage tasks.

LangGraph, developed by LangChain Inc., introduces a graph-based representation of agent interactions where nodes correspond to agent states and edges represent state transitions. This formalism enables rigorous reasoning about agent workflows, including loop detection, termination conditions, and backtracking strategies. LangGraph supports both deterministic and probabilistic transition policies, providing flexibility in agent orchestration strategies.

These systems demonstrate the feasibility of LLM-driven multi-agent collaboration but primarily target general-purpose domains. Their application to geospatial and hydrological tasks remains underexplored, with limited integration of spatial data structures, numerical solvers, or visualization capabilities. Furthermore, existing frameworks lack the standardized tool discovery mechanisms provided by the Model Context Protocol, constraining interoperability with specialized computational resources.

\subsection{Model Context Protocol Architecture}

The Model Context Protocol (MCP) establishes a standardized interface between LLMs and external tools, enabling dynamic tool discovery, capability advertisement, and structured invocation. The protocol defines three core components: the MCP server that exposes tools with metadata descriptions, the MCP client that orchestrates tool execution on behalf of the LLM, and the MCP transport that facilitates communication between client and server.

Tool discovery follows a capability-based matching paradigm where servers advertise available operations through structured descriptions including input schema, output format, and semantic annotations. The LLM queries this registry to identify tools appropriate for user intent, eliminating the need for pre-specified tool bindings. This dynamic architecture enables seamless integration of new tools without modifying the LLM or orchestration logic, facilitating extensible system evolution.

The MCP specification supports multiple transport mechanisms including standard HTTP/REST, Server-Sent Events (SSE), and WebSocket protocols, accommodating diverse deployment scenarios and performance requirements. The SSE transport provides efficient streaming of tool outputs and intermediate results, enabling real-time feedback during long-running operations鈥攁 critical capability for computationally intensive hydrodynamic simulations.

While the MCP framework has seen adoption in developer tools and productivity applications, its application to geospatial computing and hydrodynamic modeling remains novel. Our work represents, to the best of our knowledge, the first comprehensive implementation of an MCP-native architecture for spatial intelligence, leveraging the protocol's extensibility to integrate diverse geospatial tools within a unified LLM-accessible framework.

\subsection{Spatial Intelligence in Water Resources}

The concept of spatial intelligence encompasses the integration of geospatial data, spatial reasoning, and domain knowledge for decision support in environmental management. In water resources, spatial intelligence applications include flood risk mapping, watershed delineation, drainage network extraction, and site suitability assessment for infrastructure development.

Traditional spatial intelligence systems rely on Geographic Information Systems (GIS) such as ArcGIS, QGIS, and GRASS GIS, which provide graphical interfaces for spatial data manipulation and analysis. While powerful, these systems require specialized training and manual operation of geoprocessing tools, limiting accessibility to domain experts without GIS expertise. Furthermore, the sequential nature of GUI-based workflows impedes automation and batch processing of multiple scenarios.

Recent advances in cloud-based geospatial platforms, including Google Earth Engine, Microsoft Planetary Computer, and AWS Ground Segment, have democratized access to large-scale Earth observation data and computational resources. These platforms enable server-side processing of satellite imagery and geospatial datasets through web APIs, reducing local computational requirements. However, they maintain the programmatic interface paradigm that still requires technical expertise for effective utilization.

The integration of LLMs with geospatial systems represents an emerging frontier. Early efforts include conversational interfaces for spatial querying, natural language generation of thematic maps, and automated workflow composition for common GIS tasks. However, these systems typically operate at the data access and visualization level, lacking the numerical modeling capabilities required for hydrodynamic simulation and flood prediction.

Our work bridges this gap by embedding a complete hydrodynamic modeling capability within an LLM-accessible framework, enabling spatial intelligence that extends beyond data query and visualization to predictive simulation and scenario analysis.

\section{System Architecture}

\subsection{MCP-Native Microservice Design}

The S-AI platform adopts a microservice architecture where each computational capability resides in a dedicated MCP server exposing specialized tools through the Model Context Protocol. This design achieves several critical objectives: isolation of computational concerns, independent scaling based on demand, fault tolerance through service decoupling, and seamless addition of new capabilities without disrupting existing services.

The system comprises eight MCP servers deployed on distinct network ports, each serving a specific domain within the hydrodynamic modeling workflow:

\begin{itemize}
    \item \textbf{GIS Server (Port 5001)}: Exposes 8 tools for geospatial data processing including vector I/O, spatial query, coordinate transformation, and topology operations. Implements support for GeoJSON, Shapefile, and GeoPackage formats with automatic schema detection.
    \item \textbf{Data Server (Port 5002)}: Provides 5 tools for data acquisition, preprocessing, and quality control. Handles DEM import, raster resampling, nodata value handling, and metadata extraction from GeoTIFF headers.
    \item \textbf{Knowledge Server (Port 5003)}: Offers 4 tools for accessing domain knowledge including parameter tables, design specifications, and regulatory standards. Stores Manning roughness coefficients, SCS curve numbers, and design storm parameters in structured JSON format.
    \item \textbf{Map Server (Port 5004)}: Supplies 4 tools for map rendering and 2D visualization. Generates Leaflet-compatible GeoJSON layers, applies color ramps for depth and velocity representation, and produces interactive web maps with legend controls.
    \item \textbf{Hydro Server (Port 5005)}: Delivers 5 tools for hydrological computations including design storm generation, runoff calculation, and time series analysis. Implements Chicago storm pattern temporal distributions and SCS-CN methodology for infiltration modeling.
    \item \textbf{Flood Server (Port 5006)}: Provides 5 tools for flood simulation including 2D hydrodynamic modeling, inundation mapping, and risk assessment. Solves the diffusion wave approximation of shallow water equations with Manning friction.
    \item \textbf{Raster Server (Port 5007)}: Exposes 4 tools for raster operations including flow direction calculation (D8 algorithm), flow accumulation, watershed delineation, and stream network extraction.
    \item \textbf{Web Server (Port 3000)}: Hosts the frontend application providing user interface, SSE streaming, and WebSocket connections for real-time updates. Serves the 3D visualization engine based on Three.js.
\end{itemize}

Each server implements the MCP specification through FastAPI endpoints that expose tools via the \texttt{/tools} endpoint for capability advertisement and \texttt{/call} endpoint for tool invocation. The servers maintain independent health monitoring and logging, enabling graceful degradation if individual services become unavailable.

\subsection{LLM-Driven Intent Routing and Orchestration}

The heart of the S-AI architecture is the intent routing engine that translates natural language user queries into orchestrated tool execution sequences. This engine comprises three components: the LLM client for semantic understanding, the capability registry for tool discovery, and the execution engine for workflow orchestration.

The LLM client integrates with GLM-5.1 via the ZhipuAI API, supporting streaming responses and function calling capabilities. The system maintains conversation context across multiple turns, enabling multi-stage workflows where initial tool outputs inform subsequent parameter specification. The client implements retry logic with exponential backoff for network resilience, ensuring reliable communication with the LLM service.

The capability registry, implemented in the \texttt{RegistryStore} class, maintains a dynamic inventory of available tools across all MCP servers. The registry performs periodic health checks and tool synchronization, ensuring that tool advertisements reflect the current system state. When the LLM generates a tool call, the registry resolves the tool name to the corresponding server endpoint and forwards the invocation request.

The execution engine manages the orchestration of tool calls, handling dependencies between operations, parallelizing independent tasks, and aggregating results for presentation to the user. The engine supports both sequential and parallel execution patterns, automatically determining parallelism based on tool call dependency analysis. For hydrodynamic simulations, the engine detects the full workflow chain: DEM processing $\rightarrow$ mesh generation $\rightarrow$ parameter specification $\rightarrow$ model execution $\rightarrow$ post-processing $\rightarrow$ visualization, and executes it with minimal idle time.

\subsection{Tool Discovery and Dynamic Orchestration}

The S-AI platform implements a capability-based tool discovery mechanism that matches user intent to available computational resources without requiring pre-specified mappings. This mechanism operates through semantic analysis of tool descriptions and parameter schemas, enabling the LLM to identify appropriate tools even for novel queries not anticipated during system design.

Each tool advertisement includes rich metadata: a human-readable description of the tool's purpose, a structured JSON schema defining input parameters with types, constraints, and default values, an output schema specifying the structure of return values, and semantic tags indicating the domain and operation type (e.g., "hydrology:runoff-computation", "spatial:flow-direction").

The LLM leverages this metadata to construct tool calls with appropriate parameters, automatically inferring values from context when not explicitly specified. For example, a query like "simulate flooding for a 50-year storm over Diebu County" triggers the following inference process:

\begin{enumerate}
    \item Identify the domain as flood simulation, matching tools tagged with "flood:simulation"
    \item Select the appropriate tool (e.g., \texttt{simulate\_inundation}) from the Flood Server
    \item Extract the return period parameter "50" from the query text
    \item Infer the location "Diebu County" as a spatial extent, triggering DEM loading
    \item Generate a Chicago storm pattern with 50-year return period as the rainfall forcing
    \item Execute the simulation with inferred parameters
    \item Format results as 3D visualization and depth statistics
\end{enumerate}

This inference capability dramatically reduces user burden while maintaining flexibility for expert users who prefer to specify all parameters explicitly.

\subsection{Data Flow: Natural Language to Visualization}

The S-AI system follows a unidirectional data flow from natural language input to geospatial visualization output, with multiple parallel branches for independent computations. The flow comprises five stages:

\textbf{Stage 1: Intent Parsing:} The LLM analyzes the user query, identifies the core intent (e.g., flood simulation, runoff calculation, risk assessment), extracts explicit parameters, and infers implicit requirements. The LLM generates a structured task specification including the sequence of tools to invoke and the parameter bindings for each.

\textbf{Stage 2: Data Preparation:} Parallel tasks load and preprocess required geospatial datasets. The DEM is loaded from GeoTIFF, nodata values are identified and masked, coordinate systems are verified and transformed if necessary, and spatial extents are clipped to the region of interest. These tasks execute in parallel to the tool discovery phase, minimizing startup latency.
